<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="sid-19693845">
    
    <title>Service Contract</title>
    <section id="sid-19693870">
      
      <title>Generating a Contract</title>
      <para>The Savara Eclipse tooling includes the ability to generate contracts  from source models. These models can vary, including (currently)  choreographies and BPEL process definitions.</para>
      <para>Select the "Savara-&gt;Generate-&gt;Contract" menu item associated with the context menu of the source model. For example,</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
<title>Menu item for generating a service contract</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="author/download/attachments/19693870/GenerateContractMenu.png" width="5in" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>This will display a dialog window to allow the user to select how  each role, identified within the source model, should be generated as a  service contract:</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
<title>Dialog for specifying the service contract information for each role in the source model</title>
         <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="author/download/attachments/19693870/GenerateContractDialog.png" width="3in" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>
        The
        <emphasis role="italics">"Service Role"</emphasis>
        check box is used to indicate whether that role, within the source model, should result in a service contract being created.
      </para>
      <para>
        The
        <emphasis role="italics">"Contract Type"</emphasis>
        field displays a list of contract  generation types. This list will be dependent upon the source model  type, and so will not be discussed in detail here.
      </para>
      <para>When the OK button is pressed, each of the contracts for the enabled roles will be created with their relevant artifacts, within the current Eclipse project containing the source model.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
