<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter id="bpel">
	<title>BPEL</title>

	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>
This section will describe generation and conformance checking features related to WS-BPEL.
		</para>
		
		<para>
This initial release provides basic support for generating BPEL processes from a choreography 
description. Subsequent releases will also provide conformance checking, to ensure that changes 
to a BPEL process are validated to ensure the process remains conformant with the choreography.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
      	<title>Generating a BPEL process</title>
		<section>
			<title>Overview</title>
			<para>
This section explains how to generate a template BPEL process from architectural and design
artifacts.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Generating the BPEL Process from a Choreography Description</title>
			<para>
When the choreography description has been completed, and has no errors, the user should select
the "SAVARA->Generate->Service" menu item from the popup menu associated with the choreography
description (.cdm) file.
			</para>

		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="en-US/images/GenerateServiceMenu.png" width="4in" />
		</imageobject>

			<para>
When the dialog window is displayed, it will contain the list of services that can be generated,
along with the project names that will be created, and the target service type for each.
The user can unselect the services they do not 
wish to generate (also using the 'Check All' or 'Clear All' buttons).
			</para>

		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="en-US/images/GenerateService.png" width="5in" />
		</imageobject>

		<para>
If there is a problem with the name of the project select, such as invalid characters used in the name, 
or the project name already exists, then it will be displayed in red.
			</para>

		<para>
Once the BPEL is generated, it can be viewed using the Eclipse BPEL editor, e.g.
		</para>

		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="en-US/images/genbpel3.png" width="4in"  />
		</imageobject>

		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Limitations with the current CDL to BPEL mapping</title>

			<para>
This initial version of the BPEL generation is primarily targeted at generating the interactions 
and grouping constructs. These are the important components that will be required when doing 
conformance checking as part of the next milestone.
			</para>

			<para>
This means that assignments and conditional expressions are not currently generated. The 'when' 
construct in CDL (also known as the blocking workunit) is also not currently handled. This may possible 
be implemented using flow links.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

</chapter>

